Martin Agronsky Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Martin Agronsky Papers1907-1999 (bulk 1940-1990)
MSS84841
Agronsky, Martin, 1915-1999
27,700 items 79 containers 31.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Radio and television journalist. Appointment books, awards, radio, television, and film scripts, speeches, writings, and research material pertaining to Agronsky's career as a radio and television journalist.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Agronsky, Martin.; Eichmann, Adolf, 1906-1962--Trials, litigation, etc.
Subjects
Cold War.; Economics.; Foreign correspondents--Asia.; Foreign correspondents--Australia.; Foreign correspondents--Europe.; Politics, Practical.; Trials--Israel.; World War, 1939-1945--Journalists.
Occupations
Journalists.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Martin Agronsky, radio and television journalist, were given to the Library of Congress by his estate in 2001. Additional material was given in 2003 by David Agronsky.
Transfers
Sound recordings, videocassettes, and a film have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the Martin Agronsky Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Martin Agronsky are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1915, Jan. 12 Born, Philadelphia, Pa.
1936 B.A., Rutgers University, New Brunswick, N.J.
1936-1937 Reporter, Palestine Post
1937-1940 Freelance newspaper reporter
1940-1943 Foreign correspondent, National Broadcasting Co.
1943 Married Helen Smathers (died 1969)
1943-1957 Correspondent, American Broadcasting Co., Washington, D.C.
1952 Awarded George Foster Peabody Award
1957-1964 Correspondent, National Broadcasting Co.
1961 Awarded Alfred I. DuPont Award
1964-1968 Bureau chief, Paris, France, and moderator of “Face the Nation,” Columbia Broadcasting System
1968 Received Emmy Award
1969 News anchor, WTOP-TV, Washington, D.C.
1969-1987 Host, “Agronsky and Company,” WETA-TV, Washington, D.C.
1971-1975 Host, “Martin Agronsky's Evening Edition” and “Agronsky at Large,” Public Broadcasting System
1999, July 25 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Martin Agronsky (1915-1999) span the years 1907-1999, with the bulk of the material dating from 1940 to 1990. The papers are organized in the following series: Correspondence, Speeches and Writings File, and a Miscellany consisting primarily of appointment books, awards, biographical material, and items related to organizations with which Agronsky was associated.
The Correspondence series contains primarily letters written by colleagues and the public to Agronsky in response to his newscasts. Incoming and outgoing letters and telegrams document communications between Agronsky and his network supervisors regarding news assignments.
The Speeches and Writings File, especially the scripts of Agronsky's newscasts, forms the centerpiece of the papers. The material dates from his career as a foreign correspondent in Europe, Australia, and Asia during World War II and continues through the Cold War years. His coverage of the Adolf Eichmann trial in Israel won him the Alfred I. DuPont Award in 1962. Other scripts include his work on documentary films. The speech file contains correspondence, notes, and texts pertaining to his lectures on political and economic subjects. Research material includes news clippings, notes, and printed matter relating to the subjects on which Agronsky frequently lectured.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in three series:
Correspondence, 1907-1991
Speeches and Writings File, 1939-1996
Miscellany, 1933-1999
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm2001084841
Container List
- Correspondence, 1907-1991 (Box 1-12)
  Correspondence and memoranda between Agronsky and his friends, colleagues, and the public relating to professional activities.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1907, 1939-1942, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1943
    - Jan.-Apr., (3 folders)
    - June-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1944, (5 folders)
  - 1945
    - Jan.-Apr., (2 folders)
    - May-Sept., (7 folders) (Box 3)
    - Oct.-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1946-1947, (5 folders)
  - 1948-1949, (5 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1950
    - Jan.-Apr., (2 folders)
    - May-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1951, (2 folders)
  - 1952
    - Jan.-Mar.
    - Apr.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1953, (7 folders)
  - 1954 (Box 8)
    - Jan.-May, (7 folders)
    - June-Dec., (7 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1955
    - Jan.-Mar., (2 folders)
    - Apr.-Dec., (7 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1956-1971, (3 folders)
  - 1972-1981, (9 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1982-1991, undated, (9 folders) (Box 12)
- Speeches and Writings File, 1939-1996 (Box 13-74)
  Broadcast and film scripts, magazine articles, research material, and speeches.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Broadcast scripts (Box 13)
    - American Broadcasting Co.
      - “At Issue”
        - Correspondence and financial records, 1953-1954, undated
        - Interviews, 1953-1954, (3 folders)
        - Prospective topics, 1951-1954, undated
      - Daily news
        - 1943, (3 folders)
        - circa 1943, (9 folders); (3 folders) (Box 14, Box 15)
        - 1944
          - Jan.-May, (8 folders)
          - June-Sept., (9 folders) (Box 16)
          - Oct.-Dec., (5 folders) (Box 17)
        - 1945
          - Jan.-Feb., (3 folders)
          - Mar.-Aug., (6 folders) (Box 18)
          - Sept.-Dec., (6 folders) (Box 19)
        - 1946
          - Jan.-Feb., (3 folders)
          - Mar.-Aug., (8 folders) (Box 20)
          - Sept.-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 21)
        - 1947
          - Jan.-Feb., (4 folders)
          - Mar.-June, (7 folders) (Box 22)
          - July-Nov., (8 folders) (Box 23)
          - Dec., (3 folders) (Box 24)
        - 1948
          - Jan.-Mar., (6 folders)
          - Apr.-Sept., (9 folders) (Box 25)
          - Oct.-Dec., (6 folders) (Box 26)
        - 1949
          - Jan.-Feb., (3 folders)
          - Mar.-June, (8 folders) (Box 27)
          - July-Oct., (7 folders) (Box 28)
          - Nov.-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 29)
        - 1950
          - Jan., (2 folders)
          - Feb.-May, (8 folders) (Box 30)
          - June-Sept., (7 folders) (Box 31)
          - Oct.
            - 2-14
            - 16-31 (Box 32)
          - Nov.-Dec., (4 folders)
        - 1951
          - Jan.-Feb., (4 folders)
          - Mar.-June, (8 folders) (Box 33)
          - July-Oct., (7 folders) (Box 34)
          - Nov.-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 35)
        - 1952
          - Jan.-Feb., (4 folders)
          - Mar.-May, (6 folders) (Box 36)
          - June-Nov., (9 folders) (Box 37)
          - Dec., (2 folders) (Box 38)
        - 1953
          - Jan.-May, (9 folders)
          - June-Dec., (8 folders) (Box 39)
        - 1954
          - Jan.
          - Feb.-July, (9 folders) (Box 40)
          - Aug.-Dec., (7 folders) (Box 41)
        - 1955
          - Jan.-Feb., (3 folders)
          - Mar.-Aug., (11 folders) (Box 42)
          - Sept.-Nov., (8 folders) (Box 43)
          - Dec., (3 folders) (Box 44)
        - 1956
          - Jan., (3 folders)
          - Feb.
            - 1-14
            - 16-29 (Box 45)
          - Mar.-Apr., (6 folders)
          - May-June, (6 folders) (Box 46)
          - July
            - 2-21, (2 folders)
            - 23-31 (Box 47)
          - Aug.-Nov., (7 folders)
          - Dec., (4 folders) (Box 48)
        - 1957
          - Jan.-May, (6 folders)
      - Program sponsors (Box 49)
        - Cancellations, 1946-1956, (7 folders)
        - Correspondence, 1950-1955
        - Expenses, 1943-1953
        - Lists, 1945-1954, undated, (3 folders)
        - Miscellany, 1947-1955, undated (Box 50)
        - Radio station affiliates, 1950-1955
        - Sales, 1946-1956, (6 folders)
        - Sponsor identifications, 1953-1955, (2 folders)
    - National Broadcasting Co. (Box 51)
      - Daily news
        - 1939-1940, (4 folders)
        - 1941
          - Jan.-July, (6 folders)
          - Aug.-Oct., (3 folders) (Box 52)
        - 1942, (6 folders)
        - 1957-1968, (7 folders) (Box 53)
      - “Emphasis,” 1960-1964, undated
      - “Look Here”
        - Correspondence, 1957-1958, 1996, undated
        - Interviews
          - 1957, (2 folders)
          - 1958, undated, (3 folders) (Box 54)
      - “The Trial of Adolf Eichmann”
        - Production material, 1961
        - Scripts, 1961
      - Unidentified scripts, undated
  - Miscellany
    - Films
      - American Workmanship, 1976
      - And One to Grow On, 1979-1980, undated
      - Coal slurry pipeline, 1980
      - Communications Workers of America, 1982, undated
      - CSX-Richmond Corp., 1984
      - First Monday in October, 1980 (Box 55)
      - Hadassah Medical Organization, 1985
      - It's Child's Play, 1961
      - A Matter of Commitment, 1983
      - The National Financial Planning Quiz, 1981
      - Nazareth to Bethlehem travelog, 1961
    - Magazine articles
      - “I Will Be Back,” undated
      - Life project on Iran, 1947, undated
      - “Iran--Urgent,” undated
      - Miscellaneous, 1943-1952, undated
      - “The Partition of Palestine,” 1937
      - “The Public and the Act,” 1970
      - “The Voice of the Supreme Court,” 1955-1956
    - Radio and television guest appearances, 1968, 1979-1988
  - Research material (Box 56)
    - Abortion, 1964, 1974, undated
    - American Jewish Congress, 1963-1964, (2 folders)
    - Atomic energy, 1947-1950, undated
    - Automotive advertising, 1956
    - Battery additive material, 1949-1953, undated
    - Bernstein, Leonard, 1976
    - Bomb shelters, 1961, undated
    - Burch, Dean, 1964, undated
    - Burrows, Abe, undated
    - Carter, Jimmy, 1977, undated (Box 57)
    - Censorship, 1952
    - Central America, 1985
    - Central Intelligence Agency, 1965-1966, 1974-1977, 1985, undated
    - Civil liberties, 1949-1955, undated, (2 folders)
    - Communism, 1948-1955, 1963, 1973, undated (Box 58)
    - Condon, Edward U., 1948-1949, undated
    - Crossfield, Scott, 1955-1958, undated, (2 folders)
    - Cuban missile crisis, 1963, undated
    - Democratic Party, 1944, 1952, 1981
    - Disarmament, 1983-1986, undated
    - Dulles, John Foster, 1952-1957, undated
    - Eastern Europe, 1940-1942, undated
    - Economics, 1952-1955, 1977-1978, undated (Box 59)
    - Education, 1952-1954, 1963, undated
    - Eichmann, Adolf, trial of
      - Court documents, 1961, (5 folders); (2 folders) (Box 60)
      - Fact sheets and news releases, 1960-1961, undated, (2 folders)
      - Memoranda and notes, 1960-1961, undated, (3 folders)
      - Printed matter, 1947-1961, undated, (6 folders) (Box 61)
    - Elections
      - 1948
      - 1950-1964, 1980-1988, undated, (7 folders) (Box 62)
    - Fast, Howard, 1957, undated
    - Finance
      - 1945-1954, (3 folders)
      - 1957, 1969, undated (Box 63)
    - Foreign policy, 1950-1955, 1963-1967, 1978, 1984-1986, undated
    - Fulbright, J. William, 1959-1965, undated
    - Germany, 1949-1954, 1961-1964, undated
    - Goldwater, Barry, 1964, undated
    - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1963-1968, undated, (4 folders)
    - International languages, 1951-1954, undated
    - Israel, 1958-1988, undated, (5 folders) (Box 64)
    - Kennedy, John F., assassination investigation, 1970
    - King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1956-1957, undated
    - Labor organizations, 1952-1964, 1977, undated
    - Lattimore, Owen, 1953-1954, undated
    - League of Nations, 1937, 1974 (Box 65)
    - Leopold, Nathan F., 1957, undated
    - McCarthy, Joseph R., 1954, 1962, undated
    - Miscellaneous
      - Notes, undated, (4 folders)
      - Printed matter
        - 1948-1955, (3 folders)
        - 1956-1980, 1986, undated, (3 folders) (Box 66)
    - National Endowment for the Arts, 1976, undated
    - Nicaragua, 1985
    - Nuclear weapons, 1946-1955, 1964, 1978, undated
    - Pearson, Lester Bowles, 1954-1961, undated
    - Perkins, Anthony, 1958, undated
    - Post World War II economy, 1949-1954, undated (Box 67)
    - Public broadcasting, 1954, 1973, undated
    - Racial discrimination, 1954, 1963-1968, undated
    - Rayburn, Sam, 1961, undated
    - Republic of the Congo, 1961-1962
    - Scientists and national security, 1948-1954, undated
    - Southeast Asia, 1950-1953, 1961-1971, undated, (3 folders)
    - Stanley, Kim, undated
    - Stevenson, Adlai E. (1900-1965), 1952, undated (Box 68)
    - Summit meetings, 1960, 1986, undated, (2 folders)
    - Taft, Robert A. (1889-1953), undated
    - Tennessee Valley Authority, 1954
    - USSR, 1953, 1961-1964, 1979-1980, undated
    - U.S. Senate, 1952, 1964-1966, undated
    - U.S. Supreme Court
      - 1947-1955, (2 folders)
      - 1956, 1968, 1974-1977, undated (Box 69)
    - Violence and television, 1969-1977, undated
    - Von Braun, Wernher, 1957
    - Voskovec, George, immigration case, 1950
    - Webb, Jack, undated
    - Weil, Joseph, 1946-1954
    - Welfare, 1945
    - Women's liberation, 1975-1977, undated
    - World War II, 1943-1944, undated
    - Yates, Sidney R., 1957, 1978
    - Yugoslavia, 1955
  - Speech file (Box 70)
    - 1942, 1947-1975, (12 folders)
    - 1976-1980, (10 folders) (Box 71)
    - 1981
      - Jan.-Apr., (5 folders)
      - May-Dec., (5 folders) (Box 72)
    - 1982
      - Jan.-Sept., (13 folders)
      - Oct.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 73)
    - 1983-1985, (11 folders)
    - 1986-1990, undated, (20 folders) (Box 74)
- Miscellany, 1933-1999 (Box 75-79)
  Appointment books, awards, biographical material, lawsuits, and correspondence relating to organizations and television programs.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Appointment books (Box 75)
    - 1982-1986, (3 folders)
    - 1987 (Box 76)
  - Awards
    - Alfred I. DuPont Award, 1961
    - George Foster Peabody Award, 1952-1953, undated
    - Hall of Distinguished Alumni, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, N.J., 1995
    - Heywood Broun Award, 1948-1949
    - Miscellaneous, 1952-1953, 1984, undated
    - National Headliners Club, 1948
    - Sigma Delta Chi Radio Award, 1949
  - Biographical material
    - 1933, 1939-1944, 1950-1959, (2 folders)
    - 1960-1991, 1999, undated, (6 folders) (Box 77)
  - Jerusalem Post, 1945-1953
  - Lawsuits
    - Alexander v. Agronsky, 1981-1982
    - Reed v. Agronsky, circa 1944
  - Organizations (Box 78)
    - National Theatre Corp., 1980-1986, undated, (4 folders)
    - Radio Correspondents Association, 1948-1953, undated
  - Photographs, 1939, 1950-1983, undated
  - Telephone messages, 1980-1981
  - Television programs (Box 79)
    - “Agronsky and Company,” 1974-1987, undated, (2 folders)
    - “Evening Edition,” 1971-1976, undated, (2 folders)
    - “Hindsight,” undated
    - Proposals, 1963, 1988